Today, let's start from the beginning.
今日はまず、一つ目から見ていきましょう。
Even if *interest rates* fall,
金利が下がっても、
this is why home prices don't rise right away.
住宅価格がすぐに上がらない理由です。
In the past, the formula was simple.
以前は、この方程式は単純でした。
When rates went down,
金利が下がれば、
borrowing became less burdensome.
ローン負担が軽くなりました。
Then more money flowed into the market,
すると資金が市場に流れ、
and buyers stepped in.
買いが入りました。
So home prices,
そのため住宅価格も、
responded almost immediately.
すぐに反応しました。
But that's not the case now.
でも今は違います。
This formula,
この方程式は、
doesn't work *automatically* like it used to.
以前のように必ずしも通用しません。
Even Seoul's apartment market,
特にソウルのマンション市場も、
doesn't move right away.
すぐには動きません。
Why is that?
なぜでしょうか。
Because real estate now,
今の不動産は、
doesn't move on interest rates alone anymore.
金利だけでは動かないからです。
In today's market,
今の市場は、
you have to look at people's *sentiment*.
人々の心理を見なければなりません。
You also have to look at income,
所得も見なければならず、
and the economic outlook too.
景気見通しも見なければなりません。
If the future feels uncertain,
先行きに不安があれば、
even a small rate cut won't get people moving.
金利が少し下がっても動きません。
The backdrop makes it even clearer.
背景を見ると、さらにはっきりします。
In the past,
過去は、
as soon as loans became easier to get, people bought.
ローンが借りやすくなれば、すぐに買っていました。
Now it's different.
今は違います。
Across the Korean economy,
韓国経済全体に、
uncertainty is high.
不確実性が大きいからです。
There are concerns about slower growth,
景気減速への懸念があり、
and household debt is still a heavy burden.
家計債務の負担も大きいです。
Real income feels stuck.
実質所得も伸び悩んでいます。
In this kind of environment,
こうした状況では、
even if rates come down a little,
金利が少し下がっても、
it's hard to say,
すぐに家を買おうと、
now is the time to buy a home.
そう決断するのは簡単ではありません。
The key, in the end,
結局の核心は、
is *buyer sentiment*.
買い手心理です。
Home prices don't rise just because of the numbers.
住宅価格は、数字だけを見て上がるわけではありません。
People have to feel like,
今買ってもいいと、
now is a good time to buy.
人々がそう感じてこそ動きます。
Even in Seoul's apartment market right now,
今のソウルのマンション市場も、
some high-demand areas are holding up.
一部の人気エリアは持ちこたえています。
But overall,
しかし全体的には、
conviction is weak.
確信が弱い状態です。
Will prices go higher from here?
この先もっと上がるのか、
People just aren't sure.
よく分からないのです。
Will the economy hold up?
景気が大丈夫なのか、
They're not confident about that either.
それにも確信がありません。
Will my income hold up?
自分の所得が持ちこたえられるのか、
That's uncertain too.
ここにも不安があります。
Without that confidence,
この確信がなければ、
transactions don't come back easily.
取引は簡単には戻りません。
There's an important point here.
ここで重要なポイントがあります。
A *rate cut* is not always,
利下げがいつも良いシグナルとは、
a positive signal.
限らないということです。
Of course, rate cuts,
もちろん利下げは、
can be positive for the market.
市場にとって前向きに働くことがあります。
But on their own,
ですが、それ自体が、
they are not a magic signal.
万能のシグナルではありません。
In fact, if a rate cut,
むしろ利下げが、
is meant to prevent an economic downturn,
景気後退を防ぐための対応なら、
people read it differently.
人々の受け止め方は変わります。
Oh,
あ、
maybe things aren't looking good.
状況が良くないのかもしれない。
That's how they may take it.
そう感じることがあります。
Then even if lending conditions improve,
すると融資条件が良くなっても、
they don't immediately start buying aggressively.
すぐに強気で買いには向かいません。
Instead, they try to protect their *cash*.
むしろ現金を守ろうとします。
Right now, this kind of sentiment,
今はこうした心理が、
has an even bigger impact on the market.
市場により大きく作用します。
That's why even if rates fall,
だから金利が下がっても、
you shouldn't assume,
住宅価格が自動的に上がる、
that home prices will automatically go up.
そう考えてはいけません。
There's one more thing to watch.
もう一つ見なければならないことがあります。
Seoul apartments, too,
ソウルのマンションも、
do not all move together.
一斉に同じようには動きません。
Even under the same rate environment,
同じ金利環境でも、
prime areas respond differently.
中心エリアは違う反応を見せます。
Places with strong locations,
立地が良く、
and solid demand,
需要がしっかりしている場所は、
can hold up or even rebound somewhat.
持ちこたえたり、一部反発したりします。
Outlying areas are different.
逆に郊外は違います。
In areas with weaker demand,
需要が弱い地域は、
the response is much slower.
反応がはるかに鈍いです。
Why does this gap happen?
なぜこの差が生まれるのでしょうか。
Because today's market,
今の市場は、
looks at more than just *rates alone*.
金利一つより、
It looks at supply conditions,
もっと多くの条件を見ているからです。
whether local demand is there,
供給がどうか、
whether incomes can support prices,
地域に需要があるか、
and whether sentiment is recovering.
所得環境が支えになるか、
These factors have become more important.
心理が回復しているか、
In the end, the simple formula from the past,
こうした要素のほうが重要になっています。
has lost much of its power.
結局、以前の単純な方程式は、
Now you have to look at the market more broadly.
力が弱まっています。
So then,
これからは、もっと立体的に見る必要があります。
what should we be watching now?
では今、
First,
何を見るべきでしょうか。
whether buyer sentiment is recovering.
第一に、
You need to see whether people are done waiting,
買い手心理が戻っているかです。
and are actually starting to move.
人々が様子見をやめて、
Second,
本当に動き始めているかを見る必要があります。
whether *transaction volume* is picking up.
第二に、
Before prices recover, transactions have to come back first,
取引量がついているかです。
for the momentum to continue.
価格より先に取引が戻らなければ、
Third,
流れは続きません。
whether demand is recovering by area.
第三に、
Even within Seoul,
地域ごとの需要回復です。
you need to see which areas move first,
ソウルの中でも、
and watch the gap between them.
どこが先に動くのか、
Only when these three come together,
その差を見なければなりません。
does a rate cut translate into actual price gains.
この三つがそろってこそ、
To sum it up.
利下げが実際の価格につながります。
Today's market,
整理してみましょう。
can't be explained by a rate cut alone.
今の市場は、
What matters more,
利下げの一言では説明できません。
is what kind of signal people take from it afterward.
その後に、
If they feel anxious,
人々がどんなシグナルを受け取るのか、
rates can fall and transactions still won't pick up.
そこがより重要です。
If they feel confident,
不安を感じれば、
that's when the market starts moving.
金利が下がっても取引は増えません。
So going forward,
確信を感じれば、
don't just watch rates.
そこから市場が動きます。
You also need to watch *sentiment*, *transaction volume*, and *local demand*,
ですからこれからは、
together.
金利だけを見るのではなく、
The direction of home prices,
心理、取引量、地域需要を、
depends more heavily on these three factors.
あわせて見ていく必要があります。
What is your area like right now?
住宅価格の方向は、
Are you seeing the impact of rates right away?
この三つにより大きく左右されます。
Or is it still quiet?
皆さんの地域は今どうですか。
Leave a comment,
金利の影響はすぐに見えますか。
and let's take a look together.
それともまだ静かですか。